Hello everyone very good morning and
welcome to an academy a one-stop
destination for the English medium civil
services aspirants. So before we start
can you please let me know if the audio
video is fine because we are facing a
technical issue before we could start.
So I would like to get a confirmation
before I begin if the audio is clearly
visible and the video if it is clearly
visible.
Sounds good. Okay. So welcome to the
daily Hindu news analysis. Let's begin
our discussion by first looking at the
topics that we are going to discuss from
the Delhi edition of the Hindu. I have
chosen seven important articles for a
detailed analysis.
We have five major articles relevant for
both prelims and mains exam and two
small articles which are more important
for the prelims examination. So let's
cover them comprehensively so that you
don't have to go back and read the
newspaper again. Now before I start I
have a very important announcement. ANA
Academy has been conducting the UPSC
summit which is a flagship event that
brings together top bureaucrats
and athletes, celebrities and our top
educators together as they conduct these
special classes on the UNAC Academy app
to motivate you and inspire you and
provide you the strategy and inputs
which could help you clear the UPSC
civil services examination. The summit
started yesterday. I'm sure many of you
would have attended these sessions today
as well. The summit continues and we
have some exciting sessions lined up
from our top educators and as well as by
several retired bureaucrats, serving
bureaucrats, stop toppers etc. So do
ensure you attend these sessions live on
the anac academy app and the link for
the same is provided in the video
description below. And if you want the
PDF of the Hindu analysis session,
please join my telegram channel by
scanning the QR code. After the session
ends, I'll be sharing the PDF over here.
So with this, let's get started and look
at the first article. On page number 12,
there's an important article related to
disaster management and environment and
ecology.
This topic is related to a recent
disaster, a industrial disaster that
occurred in Telangana.
I'm sure many of you would have read
about this development last week. There
was a tragic blast at a pharmaceutical
plant on the outskirts of Hyderabad and
nearly 39 workers were killed in this
tragic accident. It was a massive
explosion that was reported at a
pharmaceutical plant.
So this industrial tragedy which has
occurred in Telangana reminds us of the
risks of industrial disasters. How can
we approach industrial disasters from a
disaster management point of view and
what really happened at this plant in
Telangana? Were there any shortcomings
with regard to the regulatory norms with
regard to the safety norms and
procedures?
Because in India we keep on hearing
about these industrial accidents and
tragedies. Every year there are multiple
such incidents. Either there is a boiler
blast or the leakage of a hazardous
chemical or a fire accident or such
explosions which keep on recurring in
India's factories and industries. And
this not only affects the workers, it
affects the entire sector.
It hurts the image of India as well. And
there is a devastating long-lasting
impact that is left behind through such
industrial tragedies and disasters.
After all, India has suffered one of the
world's worst industrial disasters, the
Bopal gas tragedy back in 1985. And it
appears we haven't learned our lessons.
In the last four five years alone, there
have been multiple industrial tragedies
and innocent workers and people have
people have paid the price.
So this points towards the
responsibility of
the industry, the factory owners,
the responsibility of the government and
the authorities.
The question is are they being held
accountable for these lapses and
failures as many of the industrial
disasters can be entirely avoided. So to
understand this we need to dive deep
into this topic. Understand what exactly
happened at this pharmaceutical plant in
Telangana.
Initially the explosion at the pharma
plant in Telangana was expected to be a
high pressure blast most likely
triggered by a hazardous chemical or a
hazardous liquid. But experts have ruled
out this cause and initial studies have
already shown that this was most likely
a dust explosion. So what is a dust
explosion? This can be an important
topic for prelims. UPSC might ask a
basic question on dust explosion which
is a recurring industrial accident.
In a dust explosion,
very fine dust which is scattered
and compressed in chambers.
When it comes in contact with oxygen and
a ignition source,
it can easily ignite and it can cause a
massive explosion.
Such fine dust explosion is often seen
in flour mills,
sometimes even in bakeries,
even in coal mines,
in grain silos
and as well as in certain industries and
factories where fine dust is produced.
So it's quite a common accident when
fine dust is dispersed in these chambers
where it is being produced under the
forces of compression confinement with a
source of ignition with the availability
of oxygen to fuel the combustion. This
flammable dust material can easily catch
fire and it can explode in a violent
manner.
So in green silos such explosions are
very common even in coal mines, bakeries
and flour mills and as well as in
certain industries especially in few
pharmaceutical industries.
Now if you look at this factory in
Telangana,
this pharmaceutical plant,
it was basically turning wood pulp
into a fine powder which is used in the
manufacturing of drugs.
When medicines are produced to carry the
active pharmaceutical ingredient,
non-reactive material is used such as
wood pulp which is turned into fine
powder. it doesn't react with the drug
or it doesn't affect the human body.
Right? These are non-reactive platforms
which are used to deliver the drug. So
using wood pulp a type of cellulose is
generated
in these pharmaceutical plants where
they basically remove the entire
moisture content from the wood pulp dry
it out and break it up into fine
powder-like substance which becomes a
non-reactive drug carrier.
This cellulose micro cellulite or
cellulose it is vulnerable to catch fire
under the right conditions and that is
what happened most likely in Telangana.
Right now the government has set up a
special committee to investigate this
accident to find out whether there were
any lapses on the part of the factory
management on the part of the
authorities and especially in terms of
following the regulations and safety
norms. So this appears to be a case of
dust explosion. So please know what is a
dust explosion and in which factories
and industries it is seen and how does
it occur. This could be a possible
prelims question. Now coming back to our
core topic which is the topic of
disaster management. Now how do we
approach industrial tragedies from a
disaster management point of view? See
industrial disasters are no doubt a
man-made disaster.
We will discuss the various causes and
contributing factors to industrial
disasters. But first it's important to
understand is there a failure of safety
norms in India? Is there a failure of
regulatory norms in India? Because these
tragedies keep on recurring
year after year. We have seen such
recurring tragedies taking place in the
country
especially where high temperature high
pressure conditions exist.
For example,
in factories where furnaces are used
in factories where boilers, industrial
boilers are used.
For example, in thermal power plants, in
metological industries, fertilizer based
industries
where wherever high temperature, high
pressure conditions exist, where
furnaces, boilers are used, explosions
have been quite common, fire accidents
have been quite common.
There are several industries and
factories that work with hazardous raw
materials
and even produce
highly toxic materials.
So in many cases the leakage of these
toxic hazardous substances into the
factory premises into the environment
has caused these tragedies.
We have seen gas explosions taking
place.
We have seen fire accidents in several
factories and industries.
We have seen structural collapse as well
in certain industries.
Now the question is why do these
incidents keep on recurring? In many
cases this is largely due to negligence
due to the failure to follow the
established protocols the failure to
implement the safety norms because see
we don't have a lack of laws and
policies and regulations. The country
has enough safety norms. There are
enough laws in this regard. We have the
environment protection act.
We have the factories act.
We have the disaster management act of
2005.
There are plenty of laws available,
plenty of laws and regulations and
policies in place. But the problem is
with enforcement.
Now if you look at the recent accident
the blast in Telangana at this
pharmaceutical plant when the disaster
response forces and the fire services
arrived at the tragedy site the green
board which is mandatory to be displayed
was completely missing.
You know what's a green board? It's also
known as a environmental display board.
In front of every hazardous factory, any
factory where there is a possibility of
pollution, environmental pollution,
where there is a possibility of leakage
of hazardous substances, these companies
factories are mandatorily supposed to
put up a green board or also known as
the environment display board. And this
is mandated by the central pollution
control board and the state pollution
control board. They are supposed to
enforce this on the ground. So if at all
there is a tragedy when fire services,
emergency services and disaster response
forces arrive at the plan to rescue the
workers and the people who are trapped
or injured they can read the board. They
they'll know what type of chemicals or
hazardous substances are involved and
accordingly they will plan their
response.
So during this tragedy in Telangana, it
was a a very prominent pharmaceutical
company by the way. It was listed on the
stock exchanges as well. So when the
response workers arrived and the
emergency services arrived, there was no
green board, no details regarding as to
what the plant was doing. So fire
services and emergency response forces,
they had no clue what to do. They had no
idea what they were dealing with.
So that clearly points towards the lack
of safety in our industrial practices,
the lack of enforcement of the
regulatory norms, the failure of the
authorities, the failure of the factory
owners.
This points towards your negligence,
failure of SOPs, standard operating
protocols
and a complete neglect of safety in the
industry
and the responsibility has to be shared
by the industry right by the entire
industry by the factory owners and by
the authorities by the government. The
government is as much responsible
as that of the industry. The failure
lies on both the sides. And this is
quite alarming. It's quite worrying
because these incidents which are
recurring every now and then, it can
harm the entire sector and the image of
the entire industry in front of the
world which could hurt our economic
prospects.
Now see Telangana is a major hub for
life sciences,
biotech and pharma industry in our
country. I don't know if you know this
almost onethird of India's pharma
production
is happening in the state of Telangana
1 of our pharma exports
is coming from the state of Telangana
alone
and what is even more important is that
onethird of global
vaccine production
is taking place in Telangana. So clearly
Telangana is a hub not just for India.
It is even a global hub for life
sciences, biotech, medical sciences,
pharmaceutical industry and such
tragedies and and incidents which keep
on recurring every now and then can hurt
the image of the entire industry
because see India is considered as a
pharmacy of the world. We are one of the
largest exporters of vaccines and
generic drugs and markets like US,
Europe,
Australia, even Africa.
They all expect
they all expect very high standards of
safety, quality, hygiene and control.
And when they see such tragedies
occurring and they also see repeated
cases coming up where the drugs were of
inferior quality or produced in plants
where safety measures were not followed.
This eventually affects the export
potential of India's drugs and vaccines.
The export potential can be compromised
because if you look at regulators in US
and Europe for example, if you look at
the FDA, the food and uh drug
administrative authority in the US. It
has very stringent standards about about
safety about quality of drugs and if
they come across such incidents they
might place a ban on the entry of
certain drugs from India. This could
hurt the entire industry the entire
sector itself.
Right? Even in Africa, there have been
many incidents where speurious and
inferior quality drugs from India have
apparently triggered a certain incidents
including uh the death of children and
patients which has led to serious
allegations against India at the global
level which hurts the export potential
of our pharma industry. So that is also
a reason why we should take industrial
safety very very seriously. Along with
maintaining the quality of the product
which is being produced, it's equally
important to focus on the safety of our
industrial processes. That is why you
need to understand what are the causes
for these industrial accidents which
keep on recurring in our country. See
there are many causes. Industrial
accidents can occur because of natural
disasters as well.
Natural disasters like let's say
earthquakes or floods, right? These
natural disasters, even cyclones for
that matter, they can cause damage to
industrial equipment and result in a
industrial accident. But apart from
that, there are several man-made factors
which are responsible for industrial
accidents.
Usually it is negligence,
poor maintenance,
failure to follow
the standard operating protocols,
neglect to repair and service
the equipment frequently.
The overall neglect
when it comes to replacing spare parts
or also the lack of training
to the professionals who are operating
the plant. All these factors are
responsible. It could even be a case of
sabotage.
Maybe a disgruntled employee could
deliberately sabotage the plant or it
could even be a case of terrorism where
a terror group might even target a
hazardous industrial facility to cause a
bigger attack. But apart from natural
disasters, sabotage and terrorism,
right, which is a completely different
game altogether, the bigger concern is
about negligence and the failure of
protocols and the lack of training and
the lack of safety norms. That is what
is more concerning.
In most accidents that have taken place,
if you take just the last 5 years for
example, in most incidents, these
accidents were preventable. If proper
maintenance of equipment was done, if
proper repair and servicing was done on
time as per the SOPs which are laid
down, if the regulatory norms were
followed,
most of these accidents, they were
essentially preventable.
So usually it's a failure of the
implementation of regulatory norms, the
neglect in the overall maintenance of
the plant because industries are looking
to cut corners. They want to reduce
their expenses, increase their profit
margin, right? And there happens to be a
corrupt nexus, a collusion as well
between some industry owners and the
authorities, the inspectors who inspect
the plants and facilities.
So this leads to poor implementation of
the regulations on the ground and these
violations eventually lead to these
tragedies resulting in loss of life.
This could damage the environment as
well resulting in ecological damage. It
could lead to destruction of property
and infrastructure.
So these disasters have a widespread
impact. The impact of industrial
disasters can be large scale.
Not only human life can be lost.
Not only people can be injured
grievously.
There could be loss of property, loss of
infrastructure
and there could even be ecological
damage. Very very serious ecological
damage can be witnessed.
In fact, Hyderabad has already become
quite notorious for alarming levels of
pharmaceutical water pollution in the
Musi River.
The Musi River is rated as the 22nd most
polluted river in the world on the index
of pharmaceutical water pollution
because the water of the Musi is highly
contaminated with active pharmaceutical
ingredients which is directly released
from the pharma industry and the biotech
and life science industries that are
present present around the outskirts of
Hyderabad. This also points towards very
poor pollution control and pollution
standards which are being followed.
Essentially means the effluents are not
being treated. They are being directly
released into the water body and the
Musi River reports alarming levels of
drug presence and API presence which is
even contributing to antimicrobial
resistance.
And these are very serious concerns and
authorities are not acting upon it.
they're failing to implement the
existing regulations.
So what can be done from a disaster
management perspective? See when you
look at disaster management, disaster
management provides for a structured
response. It provides for a holistic
response.
Under the disaster management act of
India, we have a three-step cycle which
has been created.
We have the pre- disaster phase,
during disaster phase
and post disaster phase,
India has adopted a cyclical approach to
disaster management
and a structured response to disaster
management. So in pre- disaster that is
before the disaster can occur you focus
on planning, you focus on preparedness.
This is where regular audits have to be
conducted. The regulatory norms have to
be strictly enforced. Adequate early
warning systems can be installed to
prevent the tragedies from uh escalating
or to provide a prior warning and
forecasting
for example to detect smoke and fire.
Alarms and sensors can be installed.
Today AI can be better used to detect uh
any possible structural failure as well
in the component and the equipments used
in factories and industries.
Right. So, planning and preparedness
which covers implementation of the
regulatory norms, ensuring regular
security audits, implementing early
warning systems
and also developing the capabilities to
deal with those disasters. That all
happens in pre- disaster phase under
planning and preparedness. Then during
disaster when the disaster has occurred
or when the disaster is still ongoing
the focus will shift to emergency
response.
The focus will be on immediate relief,
rescuing as many people as possible,
saving lives, giving immediate uh first
aid and health uh access so that those
who are injured they could be their
lives could be saved and as many people
as possible can be rescued.
So rescuing the people, saving lives and
containing the damage becomes the
priority during disaster. For this you
need professional trained forces like
the NDRF,
National Disaster Response Force who are
not only trained but well equipped to
deal with hazardous
disaster sites because these industrial
sites they could be sites of
contamination. There could be a
dangerous chemical or a gas or a fire
which is present. So the response forces
should be well equipped and well trained
to deal with these hazardous situations.
And finally post disaster what do you do
after the disaster you focus on
compensation compensate the victims
ensure that those who are displaced they
are rehabilitated and you reconstruct
you build back what was lost.
So this is how you can achieve disaster
risk reduction which is also the mantra
of the SAI framework which was adopted
by the United Nations to achieve
disaster risk reduction is the goal of
Sai framework.
You can reduce the disaster risk by
reducing the vulnerability by managing
the hazard and that is what needs to be
done in case of industrial disasters
with better enforcement of rules better
enforcement of regulations with better
implementation of safety norms.
Number of these accidents can be
prevented. The vulnerability can be
brought down. The hazard can be
contained and automatically the disaster
risk will go down.
Now if you look at industrial uh
projects for example one basic measure
that can be implemented in pre- disaster
planning is something known as zoning.
Zoning which is part of land use
planning. So when industrial clusters
and corridors are created adequate care
has to be taken that residential
neighborhoods don't come up around
industrial clusters. You might have seen
many years ago, many decades ago,
usually these industrial clusters were
present on the outskirts and suburbs of
our cities. Be it in Hyderabad, beat in
Delhi, beat in Bengaluru, in any city,
you would have seen that industrial
clusters maybe 20, 30, 40 years ago,
they were primarily on the outskirts on
the suburbs. But today, rampant
urbanization, unplanned expansion, the
illegal vein in which real estate has
expanded, it has surrounded the
industrial clusters. And today you have
dense residential colonies right in the
middle of industrial clusters right
around these industrial clusters and
many of them are hazardous industries.
Obviously when tragedies occur it will
have a widespread impact. So
implementing zoning ensuring that land
is planned properly it is utilized in
efficient manner and hazardous
industries are kept away from other
corridors is very essential to contain
and minimize the damage. This is an
essential aspect of planning and
preparedness. But thanks to rampant
urbanization, zoning has basically gone
out of the wind. So these are the
challenges that India needs to address.
There are pressing issues in front of
India because if they are not addressed,
these incidents will keep on recurring.
So take up this practice question based
on what we have discussed. Despite the
enactment of several safety laws and
institutional frameworks, industrial
disasters continue to recur in India.
analyze the causes behind this trend and
suggest measures to strengthen disaster
risk reduction in the industrial sector.
Now this is a topic which UPSC has not
asked till now. It's a highly
anticipated topic given the recent
tragedies which have occurred. So please
prepare for this and I will help you
with this question by giving you a model
approach. I will give you certain points
and the structure and the flow so that
your answer writing will start
improving. This is something we will do
regularly at least for one question
every day in the Hindu analysis. We'll
try to discuss the model answer writing
approach with some key points and the
structure especially for beginners. I
think this should be very helpful. So
please let me know if you would like us
to continue with this approach where we
discuss at least one answer along with
the answer writing approach with some
key points and the structure. So for
this particular question what you can do
first read the question carefully
understand what the question is asking.
The question is clearly focused on
recurring industrial accidents in India.
The question says we have enough laws,
we have enough regulations but still
these accidents keep on recurring. So
what's happening? What can be done? That
is the focus of the question. So start
your answer with a good introduction
about industrial disasters.
Try to define them in your own words.
You don't have to mug up and buy heart
to understand the concept. You can
express this in your own words. You can
mention that industrial disasters are
man-made disasters. Essentially, they
are sudden large scale incidents in an
industrial setting that can cause
significant loss of life which can cause
damage to property and infrastructure
and ecological damage as well because in
the industry there could be hazardous
substances and toxic substances present
which could be released into the
environment during these accidents.
So in one small paragraph maybe in two
to three lines define a industrial
disaster and cite some examples.
Whatever examples you are aware of, be
it the Bopal gas tragedy, the benchmark
case in India or any recent incident
which has been in current affairs like
the explosion that happened at the
pharmaceutical plant in Telangana or the
gas leak that happened in 2020 during
the lockdown at a LG plant in Vishaka.
Any of these incidents you are aware of,
right? Recently there was a boiler
explosion as well in one of the NTPC
plants. Any such example can be cited
here just to substantiate your argument
and your definition of industrial
disaster. Then in the body you have to
talk about the causes of industrial
disasters.
What you can do? You can try to create a
table right or simply draw a line to
create two columns and you try to list
out the reasons and what are the
causitive factors for these industrial
tragedies.
You can mention natural causes as well,
right? Natural disasters can also cause
industrial disasters. Apart from that,
please focus on the institutional
failure, the technical failure, the
human failure, the policy failure and
the pressure from urbanization which is
all contributing to increasing cases of
industrial accidents.
Maybe one one line about each cause, one
explanation trying to explain why these
accidents are occurring. For
example, how human negligence, lack of
training,
failure to follow SOPs can contribute to
accidents. Just one one line in one
small table and this would effectively
express what you're trying to uh bring
out in the answer. Then in the next part
of the body, you have to talk about the
gaps in our institutional and legal
framework in slight detail.
talk about the overlapping jurisdiction
of multiple agencies in this particular
domain. We have disaster management
authorities at the national, state and
district level. Then we have separate uh
authorities at the state level. We have
pollution control boards at central and
state level. So there is a clear
overlapping jurisdiction between various
central and state authorities and
agencies. And this leads to the shifting
of blame. One agency will blame blame
the other. one department will blame the
other.
You also need to mention
that under the existing laws such as the
factories act for example the compliance
mechanisms the audit which is needed is
very very poor very lacks. This is often
misused
and you can even mention the corrupt
nexus I was talking about between
inspectors and authorities and the
factory owners. They try to cut corners.
They try to violate the established
regulations. They try to go around it by
bribing the officials and they still
manage to get their licenses and
certificates even though they're not
following and complying with the safety
standards. So try to mention these
loopholes which are present in the
system. Try to expose the gaps present
in the system. So that way you are
adding some technical details as well
from a legal perspective.
Then talk about the solutions because
you have to be a problem solver as well.
It's not just important to highlight the
problems and the shortcomings. You have
to provide solutions. So in the last
part of the body, maybe try to provide
four or five suggestions as to what can
be done to prevent these industrial
disasters. Regulatory strengthening,
capacity building, better zoning and
planning, policy intervention, community
engagement. Right? I've just given you a
outline. You can add maybe one one line
under each heading and that completes
your body. And in the conclusion
try to present a way forward. Maybe
possible use a quote disasters are not
natural they are failure of planning
which is a quote by the UN office on
disaster risk reduction right you can
try to use such quotes if you can
remember it or don't worry about quotes
just talk about the core topic here talk
about the culture of safety which has to
be promoted
point out that the lack of safety in our
industries is because we lack that
culture right there is a habit to
violate the regulations and norms. Talk
about the importance of building that
culture of safety and try to elaborate
upon this. What can be done? How can we
build more accountability? How can we
ensure these accidents don't recur on
those lines? Try to end your answer and
that will make for a a very good
structure with all the relevant points
with sufficient examples. So let's see
if you guys can write an answer to this
question and please post them in the
answer se in the comment section below.
Now let's look at the next article on
page 12. We have another interesting
article
which is rel related to the language
wars, the language divide which is
coming up in different parts of the
country. This time it's with
Maharashtra.
In Maharashtra, large protests have
erupted against the alleged imposition
of Hindi um especially at the school
level. The Maharashtra government
recently notified
the implementation of
one of the key pillars of the NAP, the
National Education Policy of 2020, which
provides for a three language formula
starting from primary schools.
In Maharashtra
both public and private schools they
already provide two languages at least
one of course being Marathi
the regional language the mother tongue
of most of the students along with
English but when it comes to the third
language recently Maharashtra government
took these measures to make Hindi as a
mandatory third language and this has
been met with protest by local political
parties and regional political groups as
they have raised
the allegation of Hindi imposition, how
NEP is being used as a backdoor by the
center to allegedly push Hindi on
non-Hindeing states because similar
allegations and concerns have come up
from other states as well from
Karnataka, Tamil Nadu, Kerala, several
non-Hindies speaking states have been
raising this allegation triggering a
huge controversy in the country that
allegedly the central government right
is imposing Hindi on other states on
non-Hindies speaking states.
So let's evaluate this debate from a
very neutral viewpoint. Let's look at
both sides of the argument. The center
says NP doesn't even mandate a three
language formula. It gives flexibility
to the states to decide what are the
three languages that will be taught. The
NP doesn't mandate the imposition of
Hindi and the central government is
right in that regard. Then where is this
allegation coming from? the allegation
that NAP is being used as a back door
with the center to push Hindi or
non-Hindi-p speaking states. Why is
there such stiff opposition? Previously,
let's say 20 years ago, we would never
see such opposition. In many states,
Hindi was always seen as a third
language in non-Hindi- speaking states.
But today, you see a strong opposition
against it. Why is this happening? So to
understand this, first we need to look
at NEP and the language policy that
Indian schools have followed. the
language system that we have followed in
our education system and what is the
best scientific method and the best
suitable method for India. Now if you
look at the previous education policy of
according to this 1986 education policy
both in public schools in government
schools and private schools
three languages were encouraged.
there would be something called as the
home language which is nothing but
usually the mother tongue of the child
right or would be the regional local
language in that particular state in
that particular region of course English
would be seen as the global link
language Hindi would be seen as the
national link language generally this is
what was followed in several schools
across the country
I'm sure many of you who grew up in this
schooling system right you would have no
objection to study different languages.
You would not only study your mother
tongue, your regional language. You
would also gain some proficiency in
English and some proficiency in Hindi at
least to hold a conversation and to
build basic communication skills because
being multilinguistic is a skill. It's a
talent and usually there wouldn't be
such opposition let's say 15, 20, 30
years ago. But today you see such strong
opposition and many of them blame the
NEP and the way in which the center is
trying to misuse the NP.
See NP,
if you look at NEP, the NEP recommends
that
encouraging children to learn in their
mother tongue, it is proven to have
benefits at a early age, especially in
the childhood formative years. Right?
When primary school children are taught
in the mother tongue itself in the
medium of instruction is also in the
mother tongue. Scientific studies have
established a better learning outcome a
better cognitive development on the part
of the child. And studies have also
parallelly shown that children have a
natural talent at a younger age to
develop multilinguistic skills. If you
expose them to let's say two, three or
even four languages, they have the
ability to inculcate them and develop
some skills at least in different
languages. And this is a skill set which
the child can use as they grow up. So,
NEP does encourage multilingualism. It
does promote
multilingualism
keeping in mind the diversity of
linguistic heritage of India. Keeping in
mind the linguistic diversity of the
nation, right? The different languages
that are spoken across the country, NEP
does focus on encouraging the linguistic
diversity and promoting multilingualism.
So where is this concern coming from?
Now if you look at the education policy
of 1968,
Hindi, English and one of the modern
regional Indian languages was always the
priority. But problem with NEP is that
though it does not mandate any third
language. It does provide for a three
language formula. It leaves it to the
states to decide as to what would be the
third language. But it does speak
heavily in favor of promoting Sanskrit
and the classical languages which is
still fair which is still acceptable. uh
as the government seeks to promote
India's rich tradition and heritage,
there is a certain push given through
the education policy to try and include
Sanskrit and the classical languages
like Tamil, Canada, Mallayalam and
others in the schooling system. But the
NAP explicitly does not tell a state to
include Hindi as the third language. It
gives the flexibility for the states to
decide. But the problem here is the
states have a point. The states have a
very valid argument.
The problem here is
the third language
it has to be provided in non-Hindi
speaking states.
The availability of teachers,
the availability of books
material and even sufficient students
opting for that language all becomes a
challenge a practical challenge for the
governments which means they have to
mobilize more resources, train more
teachers, make them available and if at
all students are looking to opt for a
third language now let's say in a state
like Tamil Nadu obviously Tamil and
English would be taught. If a third
language is introduced, let's say
malalum,
there should be enough number of
students willing to learn malalum, then
the school should be able to find and
arrange teachers, books and material.
This takes lot of effort operationally,
practically, it's very challenging to do
this.
So many states have a problem with
implementing the third language because
of this practical constraints which are
there and
the argument of imposition is coming up
these days
very strongly from states like Tamil
Nadu Kerala
Karnataka now even Maharashtra and many
other non-Hindeing states even from West
Bengal Odisa many other non-Hindi
speaking states are also
essentially complaining about the
alleged Hindi imposition by the center.
This allegation mainly comes up because
of the politics surrounding language.
Of late, some of our politicians and
political parties have been trying to
politicize the language issue for their
own benefits.
There are few national parties and
leaders who are trying to milk this
issue deliberately, trying to impose one
identity on the nation.
Though they may not be serious about it,
the statements they are making, the
rhetoric that they are delivering, it
divides the population on linguistic
lines and triggers the issues of
identity. It triggers a emotional
response as any group of people, any
group of linguistic uh people would be
proud of their linguistic heritage and
identity and if any outside attempt is
noticed to hurt that linguistic
heritage, there will be a counter
response to it. For example, Union Home
Minister Amit Sha has made very
controversial statements about Hindi
being pushed across non-Hindi-peaking
states or he recently made a very
controversial statement. Uh he said that
English speakers would be ashamed uh in
the coming days. So this is something
that hurts the sentiments the identity
that people attach with their language
and they feel that the politicization of
the issue of language it gives that
color it gives that image that the
center is trying to push a certain
language on the others and the regional
polit political parties and politicians
are no less they are exploiting it to
their own advantage in states like
Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu, Karnataka there
are various linguistic groups and
parties their main vote bank is from the
linguist IC base
right in Maharashtra the Marati vote is
a strong vote bank in Tamil Nadu right
there are many who vote on the lines of
language in Karnataka as well so there
are political parties leaders who
exploit this to their own advantage and
blame everything on the center as well
so this tutu me contest which is going
on between center and states the
unnecessary politicization of this the
rhetoric from the central government
especially from senior leaders ministers
is what triggers this controversy. It
ends up not only dividing our people but
it creates an unnecessary issue because
as I said 20 years ago when students
were learning three languages in schools
nobody had a problem with it. Everybody
thought it was a good skill to have.
More languages the better. Studies have
shown exposing children at a young age
to at least two to three languages is
very good for their cognitive
development. Even children can be
receptive up to three to four languages
at a young age.
So gradually in our schooling system we
have been used we've been accustomed to
to learning minimum three languages
maybe a fourth optional language right
maybe another Indian language or a
foreign language and this has always
worked well can't deny the fact that
English happens to be a global link
language if you aspire for jobs if you
aspire to improve your status speaking
English is absolutely essential it's not
just a colonial relic or a hangover it's
not because of that Indians are obsessed
with English. No, English is something
that fetches you a job. English is
something that fetches you a livelihood.
At the same time, Hindi can be a link
language. But when it is pushed, when it
is imposed at the cost of regional
languages, that is where the counter
response comes from.
So this linguistic debate which has been
triggered is largely an unnecessary
debate. It's purely the politics of
language which we are seeing. But
otherwise the NEP or the previous
language policies they have worked well
for India. So let me know what do you
think on this particular issue. It's a
very divisive issue. I know that. So let
me know your views on this and take up
this practice question. The NEP 2020
advocates a three language formula aimed
at promoting multilingualism in India.
That is the opening statement. It's
focused on NP's three language formula
and promotion of multilingualism.
critically examine the implications of
this formula on India's diverse
linguistic landscape and discuss the
challenges and potential benefits it
holds for the education system. You have
to talk about the challenges and the
benefits both. So, please try to
practice your answer writing using this
question. Next, we have another article
on page 12 that focuses on the ELI
scheme
which has been recently approved by the
Union Cabinet.
So, what is the ELI scheme? Let's
understand this quickly and look at the
pros and cons of this scheme. This can
be important for both prelims and means.
ELI stands for employment linked
incentive scheme which was announced by
the government of India in the 2024 2025
union budget.
In the recent budget, the government has
announced this scheme, the employment
linked incentive scheme to incentivize
the creation of jobs particularly in the
manufacturing sector.
especially the creation of firsttime
jobs to attract first-time workers into
into the industry. The focus is
primarily on manufacturing industry but
it applies for across uh the sectors. So
let's understand what are the provisions
of this scheme the ELI scheme. So this
scheme which has been approved by the
union cabinet with the allocation of
nearly 1 lakh cr rupees it is designed
to provide incentives to both employees
and employers
firsttime employees who are getting
employed in a industry in a factory
right in the manufacturing sector they
stand to receive certain incentives and
the employers who are employing them
right who are recruiting firsttime
employees these companies these
factories industries will also get a
incentive. So it incentivizes both
employees and employers. The government
is hoping to create around 3.5 crore
jobs through this incentive scheme over
the next 24 months.
It is expected to introduce around 1.9
cr beneficiaries into the workforce for
the first time creating much needed jobs
for India's youth.
So under the scheme the EPFO employee
provident fund organization
has been given the responsibility to
implement this incentive scheme and
it essentially provides 15,000 rupees in
two installments for firsttime
employees.
Those who have a salary of up to one
lakh rupees or below, they are eligible
for this incentive if it is their first
job.
The first month's salary, the equivalent
of their first month's salary or up to a
maximum of 15,000 is paid out in two
installments if they complete a minimum
service of 6 months and 12 months.
Let's say your salary is 15,000 rupees.
Right? Now you're employed for the first
time. It's your first job. Then if you
work for 6 months, the government will
deposit 7,500 rupees in your bank
account through direct benefit transfer.
If you complete one year, another 7,500
rupees in your bank account. So the
equivalent of 1 month salary or up to
15,000 rupees in two installments is
paid out which is quite substantial you
ask me because it's a incentive to
encourage the youth to take up
employment particularly in manufacturing
sector.
The employers will also get a incentive.
They will receive up to 3,000 rupees
for up to two years
if they provide for employment for more
than one year.
If they keep the employee for at least
12 months and above, this company will
now earn 3,000 rupees every year uh
every month, sorry, for the next 24
months. for 2 years 3,000 rupees per
month would be paid out by the
government by the EPFO to these
employers which becomes a very lucrative
incentive for the industry as well to
recruit first-time employees and
first-time workers. So the whole idea is
to push both the sides the demand and
supply and create more jobs.
But however there are both pros and cons
in the scheme. The advantage is that
such a incentive structure
it will definitely incentivize the
employers.
It'll incentivize them to be proactive
to specifically hire firsttime workers
creating more jobs in the market
contributing to job creation right
contributes to skill development as
well. The companies will also stand to
benefit. It'll reduce their overall cost
as they get subsidized from the
government.
It'll create much needed job
opportunities for employees,
help solve the joblessness problem being
faced by the country's youth to some
extent. So there are several advantages
of the scheme. However, there are
concerns as well which are being
highlighted. Especially labor unions and
trade unions are worried about the
scheme.
because they have seen such previous
incentive schemes have largely benefited
the employers.
They fear that these incentives being
offered by the government would be
pocketed by these companies especially
those with bigger pockets.
Initially they might recruit workers
later fire them just to get hold of the
incentives from the government. And they
also allege a corrupt nexus also between
government officials and some companies
where they ensure these funds are
channeled to companies certain big
companies so that they can financially
benefit from it. And this could be at
the cost of the employees and the
employee welfare. So trade unions, labor
unions are concerned about the possible
misuse of the scheme and how it might
unfairly benefit the employers more than
the employees.
There's also a concern about EPFO being
chosen to implement the scheme.
EPFO has no such expertise in
implementing a employment linked
incentive scheme. So the choice of EPFO
to implement the scheme is quite strange
from the government and questions are
being raised on this regard as well. So
these are some of the cons which are
attached with the ELI scheme but it does
have significant advantages.
Now coming to the next article on the
front page we have some important
updates about PM Modi's visit to
Trinidad and Tobago. Yesterday we
discussed this topic in detail I've
explained why Trinidad and Tobago in the
Caribbean region is important for
India's foreign policy and we discussed
the role of the Indian diaspora as well.
But today we will talk about some of the
initiatives that have been launched, the
agreements that have been signed. Let's
take a quick look. It's a very factual
discussion. Nothing much to explain here
but you should make a note of these
important developments
because the PM is on a visit to multiple
countries after visiting Ghana. He has
covered Trinidad, Tobago. He's uh
visiting Argentina which we will discuss
in the coming days. Maybe I'll make a
separate video on it as Argentina is
very crucial. He's visiting Brazil for
the brick summit which is being held
today and tomorrow by the way. So all
these are very important bilateral
visits and engagements. So please make a
note of the key developments uh in the
India relationship with the Trinidad and
Tobago which is one of the Caribbean
nations.
India and Trinidad Tobago have signed
key agreements in the financial space
and in the pharmaceutical space which is
going to benefit Indian companies to
access the Caribbean market. See India
has already become a global leader in
the pharma industry. We studied this
earlier as well. in the fintech space
and in the financial space there are
many Indian service based companies
which are global leaders or at least
they have a global presence. So the
Caribbean market is a lucrative market
for them. So agreements have been signed
in this regard which creates a opening
for Indian finance and fintech and uh
pharmaceutical companies to tap the
Caribbean market.
Trinidad Tobago has agreed to join India
initiatives such as the CDRI, the
coalition of disaster resilient
infrastructure and the global bofuel
alliance. The CDRI is a pet project of
PM Modi pushed by Prime Minister Modi as
India's uh leadership role in the field
of disaster management to create
resilient infrastructure around the
world which can withstand the impact of
disasters.
Given that the world is going to face
more extreme weather events in the
coming decades because of global
warming, India has launched the global
initiative called CDRI and several
countries have partnered with India to
focus on building resilient
infrastructure, disaster resilient
infrastructure. So Trinidad Tobago has
agreed to be a part of it and at the G20
which India hosted in 2023
and India hosted the G20 we launched the
global bofuel alliance with Brazil and
other countries to focus on alternate
fuels such as bofuel.
It is seen as a greener fuel compared to
fossil fuels. It is seen as a transition
fuel as well. So India, Brazil and few
other developing nations came together
along with few developed countries at
the G20 summit to launch the global
bofuel alliance. Many countries are now
joining the alliance as well including
Trinidad and Tobago. Next, India is
providing a grant for taking up high
impact projects in Trinidad and Tobago.
India will be funding quick impact
projects with each project getting a
grant of maximum of $50,000
maybe to improve the school
infrastructure in a neighborhood in
Trinidad and Tobago or maybe to create
better roads to provide let's say solar
lighting or to provide electricity
access or to provide a water tank. So
the these local high impact projects
would be funded by India. These would be
grants not loans. India would be
providing them as grants and
both sides have signed an agreement to
ensure its effective implementation. So
many such high impact local projects
will be chosen which will be funded by
India and each project will get a
maximum funding of $50,000.
So this is part of our development
assistance
that we provide
that we provide to countries in the
global south.
India is known to provide development
assistance to developing underdeveloped
nations and small island countries as
well and assist in their overall
socioeconomic development. So this is an
example of that. India has also gifted
2,000 laptops to help digitize education
in Trinidad and Tobago. We have
announced a $1 million grant to procure
agro machinery equipment to strengthen
agriculture.
And India is going to help this country
in millet cultivation, seaweed
fertilizer and natural farming
to ensure that the needs of the people
of the Caribbean region is met and also
this could boost their export potential.
Especially seaweed fertilizer has great
potential not only to increase
agricultural productivity in Trinidad
and Tobago but it can become a item of
export which can bring revenue to this
country as well. So India is going to
assist in these agricultural domains and
India has also supported the country in
the field of healthcare by donating two
sea ambulances and 20 hemoilysis units.
India has launched a cultural initiative
to train Hindu pundits. As we discussed
the other day, Trinidad Tobago has a
significant Indian community uh who are
descendants of the indentured laborers
who were transported from India 180
years ago by the British. Many of them
are Hindus, right? And they still have
the age-old connection with India. So
Hinduism remains a dominant religion in
Trinidad and Tobago and India is
building the cultural ties and for that
we have a separate program which is
being launched to train Hindu priests in
Trinidad and Tobago. Both sides have
agreed to collaborate in global south
initiatives.
India is a leader of the global south
and India wants the support of Trinidad
Tobago to build our partnership with
carryom which is a regional grouping of
the Caribbean nations. CARICOM stands
for Caribbean community. All the
Caribbean countries in the Caribbean
region, Latin America region, they're
part of the Caraccom group and India has
very close ties with with this regional
organization. So Trinidad Tobago can
give a push for India's partnership with
carryom. And finally, India has signed
agreements in the field of pharmacopia
that's basically pharmaceutical
production, pharmaceutical standards and
exports, sports and capacity building
and training. India is going to train
the bureaucrats and diplomats of
Trinidad and Tobago in our trainingmies
and institutions. So this is part of our
capacity building initiative. These are
some of the key outcomes of PM Modi's
visit. So please make a quick note of
them. Now coming to the next big
article, there has been a development
from Myanmar. As you all know, Myanmar
is going through a civil war since 2021.
Since Myanmar's military, the army, the
Tatmada
declared a state of emergency and
nullified the elections.
Since then, Myanmar is back under the
rule of the military hunda.
So this military rule has been opposed
by the pro-democracy forces.
All the political parties and
pro-democracy forces have come together
to form a national unity government and
they have even taken up arms and weapons
against the military regime forming the
people's defense force to fight back
against the atrocities that are being
committed by the military ha.
As the pro-democracy forces protested
for the restoration of democracy, these
pro-democracy protests were brutally
crushed by the military with the use of
force. Civilians have been targeted and
killed in large numbers and
disproportionate force including air
strikes are being uh used by Myanmar's
military to target the civilians.
So the opposition forces have come
together. The national unity government
which has formed a parallel government
has aligned with people's defense forces
and they are aligning with various
ethnic armed organizations.
Various insurgent groups in Myanmar
have been coming together to form a
joint alliance of sorts and they're
mounting a joint attack uh against the
military hunda over the last four years
and Myanmar has suffered significant
losses. The military regime for the
first time has lost significant
territory. It has lost a strategic
locations from its control. You can see
in the map how the control of the
military ha has reduced to just few
pockets of the country around Yangon,
Naipid etc. But most of the other parts
of the country facing India, facing
China and Southeast Asia, they have
already been taken over by the
resistance forces.
In fact, in 2023, some of the rebel
groups, including the Arakan Army, which
operates along the borders with India,
it aligned with other rebel groups and
insurgent groups to form the three
brotherhood alliance.
It aligned with other insurgent
organizations and formed the three
brotherhood alliance and together they
mounted a series of coordinated attacks
and have managed to capture vital border
points, critical cities, trading check
posts and as well as seap ports and
airports and a large part of the country
has now come under rebel control. That's
why many experts are predicting a
possible break up of Myanmar between
rebel controlled territories and the
military controlled territories.
So now the military ha which is on the
back foot which is it is seeking out
peace before the elections which have
been announced.
The military huta has promised to
conduct the next round of elections in
order to stabilize the conflict and it
has appealed to the pro-democracy forces
and the insurgents and rebel forces to
agree to talks and cooperate with the
military regime to pave the way for next
round of elections. But this clearly
appears to be a time-bying tactic, a
negotiating tactic by the military
regime because it is known to commit
brutal atrocities against all these
rebel forces and insurgents in the past.
So in response the rebel forces and
pro-democracy forces they have refused
to cooperate.
See why would they? Because they already
know they have a clear edge over the
military. Rebels are now controlling
large parts of the country including
critical strategic locations. So they
would like to see that these areas are
liberated from the military control and
uh they would look to break up these
parts for themselves. So they have
refused to cooperate and it appears that
Myanmar's military is losing ground day
by day because for nearly 60 plus years
the military hunda has dominated the
country. It has never ever showed any
sign of weakness and this is probably
the first time where the military ha is
reaching out to the rebel and opposition
forces and pleading with them to
cooperate. That tells you everything
about the situation in Myanmar. This is
something you need to monitor regularly.
It's a very fast developing situation.
Anything might happen in the coming
days. As I said, uh there might be a
complete break up of Myanmar where the
country might split into these different
territories ruled by different factions
and that will create some unique
challenges for India. That's why this is
a topic you need to constantly keep
track of. Now coming to the prelim
section, let's quickly wrap up the
discussion. Last two articles
on page seven we have an article related
to the Guinea index
is brought brought out by the World
Bank.
The Guinea Index score is a score of
inequality.
The extent of inequality in a country is
measured by the World Bank through this
index the Guinea index right which is
based on the Guinea coefficient.
Now the guinea index score is computed
based on in income, wealth and
consumption patterns in a country. These
are the parameters which matter. The
income, wealth and consumption levels.
So using this the World Bank computes
the Guinea index score which is rated on
a scale of 0 to 100.
This is the guinea scale 0 to 100. Zero
being the best score.
So it's a inverse score essentially.
Lower the score better is your
performance. If your guinea score is
zero, it means inequality doesn't exist
in that country. That country would be
the most equal country in the world in
terms of income gap, wealth gap and
consumption gap.
And score of 100 means extreme
inequality.
It means
very few people control the income,
wealth and consumption with vast
majority having no access at all to
income, wealth and consumption. So 100
is the worst score to have. Zero is the
best score to have. So lower the score,
better the performance, lower the
inequality. And India has performed
pretty well. India has been ranked as
the fourth most equal country in the
world after the Slovak Republic,
Slovenia and Belarus.
These are the top three countries
according to the World Bank report in
terms of equality and India happens to
be at the fourth place as the fourth
most equal country which is even better
than many other developed nations like
UK, China and as well as the United
States.
India's Guinea score is a 25.5
compared to the much higher score of the
other nations like UK, US, China and the
others. Now this performance of India
has been attributed to some of the
poverty elevation programs,
socioeconomic programs of the government
of India. So schemes such as uh Aayush
manat the direct benefit transfer jandan
yojana and various poverty oriented
schemes employment oriented schemes all
these schemes have been credited
credited by the world bank for India's
improving performance with regard to
reducing inequality
back in 2011 12 India's guinea score was
28.8 8 we have improved upon this in a
decade and further reduced the guinea
score to 25.5
but of course the results are debatable
because see there are many other think
tanks and experts who argue that India
is one of the most unequal countries
where just top 1% control almost 90% of
the wealth and 99% of the population is
left to feed on the remaining 10% of
wealth income and resources right and
also if you look at the top ranking
countries here. It's not that they have
a great uh credibility be it Belarus,
Slovenia, Slovak Republic which are at
the top. Their credibility is also under
question. So there are experts who have
their doubts about this report but the
government has welcomed this report and
it has given credit to the schemes and
the success of these welfare programs
for reducing inequality in India. The
next article is related to the IAEA,
International Atomic Energy Agency. The
Hindu carries a profile of the chief of
IAEA who has attracted lot of
controversy.
It has been alleged that the report of
IAEA on Iran's nuclear program
was used by Israel and US as a
justification to launch their preemptive
attacks against Iran that took place
recently.
So there is a allegation coming up
against the chief of IAEA that somehow
he colluded with Israel and US or
deliberately brought up a report which
would which could be essentially used by
Israel and US as an excuse as a ground
to attack Iran. So irrespective of this
controversy let's keep it aside doesn't
matter for us. We need to focus on the
organization. What is IAEA? What is its
role? There can be a prelims question
based on this. The International Atomic
Energy Agency. It's a intergovernmental
organization established in 1957.
It's a autonomous organization
set up through the IAEA statute.
It has its own founding treaty. So, it's
a independent autonomous organization.
Technically, it's not part of the UN
system. Is that clear? Many students
have a big confusion here. They assume
IAEA to be part of the UN. It's actually
not part of the UN system. It's a
autonomous independent organization
independent of the UN but however it
reports to the UN general assembly and
UN security council.
It does report to UNG and UNC but it is
independent of the UN system. Yeah. It
has its own founding treaty. It has its
own statute. It is headquartered in
Vienna, Austria and India is one of the
founding members. India joined IAA back
in 1957.
So what is the role of IAEA? Its primary
role is to promote nuclear
non-prololiferation to prevent the
spread of nuclear weapons technology,
promote nuclear safety and security
and promote the peaceful usage
of nuclear technology.
So this is the primary mandate of IAEA.
So it enforces the non-prololiferation
treaty.
It has a responsibility
to inspect nuclear facilities
in the non-uclear weapon states.
According to the non-proliferation
treaty, the non-uclear weapon states,
they're expected to sign a safeguards
agreement with IAEA and the additional
protocol to it. For example, India has
signed this safeguards agreement, the
IAEA safeguards agreement along with the
additional protocol and we have opened
up our civilian nuclear facilities for
IAEA inspection. So once you sign these
safeguards agreement and the additional
protocol, the non-uclear weapon states
as recognized by the NPT, right, they
will have to throw open their nuclear
facilities for IAA inspections. These
inspectors will visit and monitor the
facilities and check whether any weapons
program is being developed or whether
the safety standards and security
protocols are being followed, whether
the non-prololiferation controls are
being implemented. Right? So, IAEA gets
access to these nuclear facilities when
countries sign the safeguards agreement
and the additional protocol to it.
Then finally, please note down IAEA has
even been awarded with the Nobel Peace
Prize for the incredible work it has
done in preventing the spread of nuclear
weapons technology. It however assists
others in development of peaceful uses
of nuclear technology for the civilian
application. It also lays down the
safety security standards and protocols
which are to be followed across nuclear
plants and facilities. So this is the
role of IAEA. On this note, I bring my
discussion to an end. I hope it has been
useful. I hope you guys have understood
everything. If you did, please press the
like button, share your comments, and
don't forget to subscribe to our
channel. That is it. We'll see you
tomorrow. Take care. Have a good day.